Welcome back. Now that you
understand how
essential tracking is,
let's explore and compare
various types of
tracking methods.
The purpose of your
project plan is to
guide you through the
execution of your project.
Therefore, it will always include
at least one type
of tracking method,
and sometimes you
might use more than
one depending on what
your team needs.
The tracking methods
we'll discuss
in this video are a Gantt chart,
a roadmap, and a burndown chart.
There are many others,
but these are the few that
I'm going to focus on.
Whichever type you
choose depends on
what you deem suitable
for your project.
It's important to remember
to select something
that the entire team
can easily understand,
reference, and keep up to date.
Let's compare the tracking
methods I mentioned.
Perhaps the most
common tracking method
of all is the Gantt chart.
It's a tried and true tool to
keep your project on track.
A Gantt chart measures tasks
against time and includes
useful information,
like who will own each task and
what the order of
the tasks should be.
For this reason,
it's a useful chart
for staying on schedule
and for projects with
many dependencies or tasks or
activities or milestones that
are reliant on one another.
It's also a helpful chart for
teams with a lot
of people, because
ownership and
responsibilities are
explicitly laid out visually.
As you track and move along
sequentially over time,
this starts to look
like a waterfall;
hence, why Gantt
charts are commonly
used in Waterfall
project management.
Each task is represented by a
horizontal progress bar, and
the length of the
bar is dependent on
how much time is
allotted to the task.
The bars are stacked on top of
each other to denote
that the task at
the top must be completed before
the next one below
it can be completed.
Gantt charts typically live in
your project plan and are
updated as the
project progresses.
Another common tracking
method we have
here at Google is a roadmap.
A roadmap is best suited
for when you need
a way to track big
milestones in your project.
It's useful for illustrating
how a project should evolve over
time to a team and key
stakeholders. Here's an example:
a roadmap might list your
project's goals at the top and
a description of the approach
we'll be taking to
meet those goals.
In this example, the
goals are to increase
online business-to-consumer
sales by 20 percent year-over-year
and to increase
holiday sales to
existing customers
by eight percent over last year.
The approach details
the main tactics
your team will use
to reach your goal.
A roadmap also includes a
high-level project overview.
High-level in this context
means a concise summary,
usually three-to-four
sentences, to clearly state
the objectives and
priorities for your project.
Below the goals, approach,
and overview is a table that
maps out what the
process will entail.
In this example, our
table is divided into
quarters that reflect
the project timeline.
A quarter is a three-month period
on a company's
financial calendar.
Key milestones are
listed for each quarter.
Then, there are tasks that
each team member or
department needs to complete.
Most tasks may map to
a milestone due within
the same quarter.
In our example, the
project as a whole has
a key milestone in Q1 to
finalize inventory for
the holiday season.
The work of product testing
and finalizing suggestions for
offerings mainly falls to the
marketing and sales teams.
However, sometimes the tasks
may need to be completed in
advance to unblock another team
or milestone in future quarters.
The product and engineering
team is working
on tasks in Q1 and in
Q2 that lead up to the launch of
the refreshed online store in Q3.
In order to reach that milestone,
each department needs to
complete specific tasks,
and the roadmap tracks
both individual
and project progress
toward milestones.
Finally, there's
the burndown chart,
the most granular of the
three tracking methods.
A burndown chart measures
time against the amount of
work done and the amount
of work remaining.
Their main uses are to keep
the project team on top of
targeted completion
dates and to keep
the team aware of scope
creep as it occurs.
Burndown charts are best suited
for projects that require
a detailed, broken-down review of
each task associated
with a project,
and they're great
for projects where
finishing on time is
the top priority.
The y-axis or the vertical axis
symbolizes the number of
tasks left to complete,
and the x-axis or the
horizontal axis signifies time.
Progress gets tracked from
the upper left-hand
corner of the chart.
As the project goes along,
you'll track down, working your
way towards zero remaining tasks,
and to the right,
working your way
toward your end date.
There's typically a dotted line
for your expected or projected
progress based on the rate your
team's expected to close tasks,
and a solid line representing
your actual progress.
Before you continue
on with your project,
you'll need to decide which
tracker makes the most sense.
If you need to communicate
milestones to a large team,
you might choose a roadmap.
If you have a project with
multiple dependencies,
you might choose a Gantt chart.
If tracking tasks against
your deadline is
especially important,
then the burndown chart
might be your best option.
And you may even decide
to use more than one.
Because the tracking method
will be determined by the type
of project you're working
on, your resources,
and the project scope,
you'll probably end up
using several types of
tracking methods at some
point in your career.
In my time at Google,
I've regularly combined methods
and used a few different
types together.
For example, using a Gantt chart
to scope work at the
beginning of a project,
then switching to a
burndown chart in
the weeks before a launch to
make sure we're good to go.
Now you know a bit more about
the various types of
tracking methods,
including a roadmap, Gantt
chart, and burndown chart.
Next step, we'll focus
on understanding
continuous improvement
and process improvement.